[Music]
hey hey
welcome to connecting with code uh we're
super excited to have us uh have you
join us this summer
i'm here with my campers the way this
works
is we film these videos uh you watch
them at home
if you're a certain age where you need
help from adult you should watch it with
your adults
but if you're a certain age where you
can do it by yourself that age is up to
you
then you'll do it by yourself to give
you an idea of
ages i'm gonna switch my camera here and
i'm gonna show
uh the campers that are here with me uh
we'll start with uh with our first
camper what's your name camper
leila neila how old is neela
go into preschool yeah so neela's five
and so who's helping needless and she's
five
mommy yeah mommy's helping uh kneeling
who's our next camper and how old are
you
and how old are you bowen and so bowen's
seven and so mommy is helping neela a
lot
um and she's helping bowen just a little
less so
at seven and five they can do it with
mommy's help then i've got my campers
who do it all by themselves so first
camper doing it by yourself what's your
name
um i am keegan fisher and how old are
you i am nine years old and i am
instilled good
so he's nine but he's been coding for a
while so he's going to be doing it by
himself and our final camper
i'm mckinley and i am 10 years old and
she
is an experienced coder and she's
definitely doing it
by herself uh so that's the campers that
i have with me here today
uh before we get started uh on our first
piece of material uh well i want to do a
quick acknowledgement
uh the material here was made by me and
also bob shafer
who works at missing college i'm filming
it uh but he also
was a big part of making these things
possible
so what are we gonna do today uh so
today what we're doing is we're building
a scratch app this whole week is coding
in scratch
scratch is a website that you'll go to
to where you build things and learn how
to code hopefully a lot of people have
heard about scratch
let's show a demo of what we're trying
to make today so today we're making one
called alphabet breakfast
so this is the solution uh so you're
just kind of watching for a minute and
the solution
and the idea of this app let me go and
make a full screen here
is that you are avery so avery is
walking around collecting things and she
has to collect
food in alphabetical order so the first
thing she collected there was an apple
um anybody know what she needs to
collect next what starts with b
banana yeah i nearly got so a banana
and if i try to eat the wrong thing
let's say i tried to eat an egg next
does
eat eggs start with c not really so it
just says keep trying food should be
eaten alphabetically so i got to find a
seafood anybody
see a good seafood cake cake
and so we eat cake what comes after cake
you think
donut uh after donut
egg
and then she does a little dance
that's what we're building today it's a
long song i guess
that's what we're building today and
that's our goal and we're going to be
building it up
uh with a block based programming
language called scratch
um and we're going to be learning a lot
of great things today these are kind of
like our learning objectives maybe i'll
come
reflect on these at the end uh but what
you need to do is you need to go to this
website
scratch.mit.edu
you can see scratch was first made uh
when it was at mit
um and it's grown so much since then
when you're on this scratch page your
first choice is you can either
just get started which is great you'll
just click on create if you want
or if you like you can sign in it
doesn't matter to me if you sign in or
not
i'm in general i think that you should
because your work will will be saved
more permanently to your account
um but it's pretty easy to sign up and
if you want to do that
you can just pause the video and go do
that on your own
so campers are you ready to get started
yes yes all right everybody click on
create
when you click on create it makes a new
program
um whenever you have a new program uh
you get to see the editor here
the editor is broken into a lot of
different places
let's just talk about it some so we're
more familiar with scratch
this area right over here this upper
right is called the stage
below the stage are the different actors
that are like on the stage
um sprites ah shoot i gave it away
scratch calls them the special name does
anybody know what the special name is
sprite i gave away the answer so they're
called sprites we have one sprite right
now
but we can actually have many sprites
sprites have code so each sprite has
their own code
the code is over here in the left in the
toolbar let's drag over
one line of code so drag over move 10.
so now you can see that our cat has code
that he can run
move10 so the question is how do we run
this code
well one way to run it is to double
click on it so double click on where it
says move 10
and you'll notice something about your
mouse every time you double click it
he'll go over to the right now one fun
thing is you can also just kind of drag
him back over here
and you can double click it and you can
run it some more
eventually you'll get bored with doing
this so once you're bored with this
let's let's do some more things now
double clicking on it is one way to run
code
but a much better way to run code is to
add
a win green flag clicked so let's
look at these uh commands if you scroll
down through here there's some blue ones
uh and then there's some purple ones and
then there's some yellow ones and maybe
you call that orange
and there's a lot of commands to make it
easier to get around the commands
they're broken into categories
the category we want is events so click
on
over here on the far left where it says
events and it'll scroll you to that
section of the code
so you can kind of see that these things
they just help you scroll around
to find the right category so the most
common way to run
code is to grab this when green
flag clicked and put it and just snap it
right on top of your code
so this is what most scratch programs
look like so this is considered like the
start of the program
so our cat when the green flag is
clicked
he's going to move 10. let's try it a
couple times so click on
the green flag and he'll move he'll move
across the stage
so this is just to kind of get you
familiar with the environment
that we're working in but actually we we
don't need a cat
at all in this game if you remember
looking at the solution there are no
cats in there
so we don't need this particular sprite
so what i want to do is i want to delete
this sprite so he was just a test
to delete it some of my campers found
this already
there's a trash can icon over here and
if you click this trash can icon
the cat will be gone poof if you ever do
something like that on
accident campers how do you how do you
fix a problem if you did that on
accident
yeah command z or control z depending on
what type of computer you're on uh
that's undo so if i messed up i just hit
um control z or command z
oops that didn't work you can also go to
edit uh restore sprite and it'll just be
back right
i did want to delete them that was a
good thing to do but just know that undo
is very important uh with things you're
doing
all right now let's add a new sprite
i've got a sprite that i'm planning on
you're using
her name is avery walking so what we
want to do
is we want to add a new sprite to do
that
there's a circle down here for choose a
sprite
this circle confuses me a little bit
because what happens is when i hover
over it it like shoots up this thing
um it turns out you can ignore the thing
that pops up you can just click right on
the circle
so click right on the circle and what
we're going to do is we're going to add
a different sprite
instead of that cat and i'm looking for
one called avery walking
now i can see avery walking is right
here so i'm just going to select it
but just know that when you're looking
for sprites you can search for them in
here
you can also organize them by category
lots of options
but i want avery walking so when i click
on her
she's now into my scratch project
avery is looking pretty good
she's a little big so what i want to do
is i want to make her
a little smaller so right here is the
size
the size right now is set to 100 that
means 100 percent
of her normal size make her some amount
smaller
i'm going to go with 60. so now she'll
be able to
play this game better
right next to size you can see she's
also got what direction she's pointing
in
and you can kind of like move her around
like this
um which is kind of fun and after a
while you'll get dizzy
now sprites have different modes you can
see that right now her mode is that she
can point in any direction
i think she looks silly when she's like
walking up
um and so what i do is i switch her mode
right now the mode is set to any
directions called all around
you can also switch it to where she's
just left right or where she doesn't
rotate at all
i want to switch her mode to where she
just does left right
so i fixed her size so she's the right
size and then i switched her mode
to where she's just left right and so
now if she's pointing
anywhere to the left her sprite just
kind of looks like it's straight left
and if she's anywhere to the right she's
straight right so she's only got those
two options now it doesn't really matter
where you leave this arrow but i'm going
to put mine back to roughly 90 degrees
all right so avery is ready to go uh but
she has no code
the first thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna add a win green flag clicked
so i'm still in my events area so i can
just bring it over
and what we want avery to do is we want
her for to forever
move and follow the mouse so it's really
mean to tell people
uh to do something forever but in code
it happens all the time
so let's see if we can find the forever
statement
so the forever statement is in the
control category
control is just below events so you can
just scroll down there if you want
or you can click on this word control
and what you're doing is you're trying
to find a forever loop
so the forever loop it's the third one
down right here so just drag a forever
loop
and pop it into place so now when the
green flag is clicked
avery is going to do something forever
and right now the thing she does forever
is is nothing there's no code in there
let's add some code in there
the code we're going to add is up in
motion so go on motion
and find one that says point towards
mouse pointer
now this one's tricky because there's a
couple in here that are somewhere
uh but i want point towards mouse
pointer
some people accidentally grab like go to
or something like that but point towards
will do it so if we're pointing towards
the mouse pointer
when i run this program she should point
towards my mouse pointer now she only
points left or right
so when i run it and my mouse is over
here she points over here
and if my mouse goes on the other side
she switches direction
so she's pointing to the left she's
pointing towards the right
left right left right left right
you can also see that the code is
running in a couple of other ways first
it's outlined in yellow
so you can see that it's running because
it's outlined in yellow also the green
flag kind of appears that it's like
continually depressed
it's not sad it's just always pressed
all right
let's add some more code my camper's
doing okay
everybody good all right let's do some
movement
so just below that point towards add a
move
10 steps
and the value 10 determines how fast she
walks
so right now i'm going to go ahead and
run it and she's going to move towards
my mouse at 10.
if you want to play with speeds um every
every kid likes to do this right so you
can you can go faster
um but if she goes too fast it works out
badly right so everybody likes to do
that so i'm just showing it to you
you can go slower so if i go at two
she'll just go really slow
and i'm going to leave mine at 15 is
where i'm going to leave mine
that will appear to be kind of fast but
we're going to fix that in a minute
so you can play around with it but i'm
going to leave mine at 15 because i'm
going to do something
here in a minute that's going to make
that be the correct speed right now it's
a little fast
another problem that i have is avery
is gliding places right i want her to be
walking places
now i'm going to show you something
about avery avery has code
we can see her code here because we're
in the code tab avery also has costumes
and avery has sounds um what we
the reason we picked avery is because
she has four costumes
and if you cycle between those costumes
it'll look like she's walking
so if you picked avery then you can make
her look like she's walking
so let's let's do that let's go into
looks
because her costume like the way she
looks is in looks
and find this one called next costume
and put it on the bottom
now i'm going to warn you she's going to
walk really fast
so you can see that she walks quite
quickly as she's going around
and it's kind of comical to watch her
but it is a little
too fast
so how do we slow her down
so the way i want to slow her down is i
want to put in a short time delay
and so with a short time delay it'll
make her look
like she's walking not extremely fast
time delays are over in control so go to
control
take a wait one second
and put it down at the bottom of your
function the bottom of your forever loop
so now
we're pointing towards the mouse pointer
we're moving 10
we're switching costumes so she looks
like walks um and then we're waiting
one second you can try one second but
it's gonna be way too slow
that's quite painful and so i'm gonna
switch it to
0.1 seconds
that i think looks good enough for me
so she's walking around and it looks
like things are going well
i think i'm going to come around i'm
going to check on some of my campers to
see how they're doing
um and it'll give you a minute to get
caught up if you're falling behind
all right neil let's start with you um
so have you got yours caught up
oh neil is a little on the independent
side neila
put a big old horse in there instead of
avery walking
um it looks really good can you show
that he moves around so you do
the green flag there and then as you
move the mouse around it's going great
bowen oh what a bunch of rule followers
bowen's got a penguin on here hit it
bowen let's see yours oh and the penguin
oh that's kind of neat bowen the penguin
has a walking animation
great job you two five and seven you can
do it let's check on our
our older campers um so we've got
mckinley uh with an avery
yours is a little fast change it to 0.1
instead of zero one um and keegan's is
right there
mckinley says she knew what she was
supposed to do she just wanted it to be
fast
um i suppose that's okay all right so
the next thing we want to do
is uh avery's looking good uh avery's
walking around a white
space um let's go ahead and give her a
better background
so just like we added a sprite we're
going to add a backdrop
so in the lower right corner here
there's a circle that says choose
backdrop
go ahead and click on that circle in the
lower right corner
just like with sprites it'll take you to
a screen that lets you pick the one you
want
what i chose to do is i chose to do
bedroom one
because i thought that it would be good
to be able to hide things in there
and to kind of make it look like it's
part of the environment i don't mind if
you do something different
you can do whatever you want to do but
just pick one that you think you'd like
while you're picking that i'm going to
talk about backdrops just a little bit
the first thing i want to say about
backdrops is that you can see right now
that my sprite is selected and i can see
her code
if i ever accidentally click on the
stage now it shows my stages code so do
this for me go back and forth click on
your sprite
and you can see your sprites code is
here and then if you click on your
backdrop which is over here to the right
you can see the backdrops code which is
blank i only point that out because
sometimes people accidentally click over
there and they're like where did all my
code go
and it's because code can be different
for different sprites it can also be
different for the backdrop
and just know to bring your code back
all you have to do is click on avery
easy peasy all right let's add a new
sprite
so we want to add food for her to eat
alphabetically
and so this time i think it really would
be best if you follow along and you add
an apple
so click on choose sprite the circle
down here
and see if you can find an apple
now you can see that there's two
different sprites there's avery
and avery has code that we've written
and then there's an apple
which currently has no code at all and
you can go back and forth between them
pretty easily
the apple if you like its size you can
leave it i'm going to choose to make my
apple just a little bit smaller
maybe a 70 apple you can also put it
somewhere in your environment
maybe i'll do a 50 apple and put it on
the table to where it kind of looks like
it belongs so it's a little bit more
hidden
that's optional next let's write some
code for the apple
oh i just realized there's another
important thing that i forgot to do
whenever you're coding ask my campers
this what's an important thing to do
when you're coding campers
save it's important to save every so
often what i'm going to do is i'm going
to name my project
i'm going to name mine alphabet
breakfast
you can name your project anything you'd
like and it does auto
save but if you ever want to force it to
save you can click on file
save now so it will periodically auto
save so you don't have to keep hitting
file save now
but if you ever do something you're like
oh i want to make sure it's saved just
click on file save now
and you'll be sure that it saves back to
the apple
so the apple uh let's go ahead and do a
win green flag for for him as well so
click on events
when green flag clicked you'll find that
a lot of sprites start that way unless
you're doing something really advanced a
lot of them start this way
and what we're going to do with the
apple is we're going to decide to show
him or hide him so he's going to either
be shown or hidden
so the first thing i'm going to do is
i'm going to make sure he's shown
at when the program starts so go to
looks first
and find show now i know right now he's
shown and everything's fine
but periodically in this app he's going
to get hidden and i want to make sure he
starts off
being shown
now the next thing we want to do is we
want to forever
check to see if avery's touching the
apple so what i'm going to do next is
i'm going to add a forever loop
so i'm in control
and i drag a forever loop over
[Music]
all right now inside the forever loop we
want to check
if she's touching the apple this is one
of our our flow control statements it's
also uh in the control area
and it looks like this it's just an if
so drag this if over
and drop it inside the forever loop so
we're forever going to check
if something is happening now the way
you read this is it says
if and then this diamond shape is the
condition so if this condition is true
then run this code now let's find a good
condition to put in here
go into sensing so we want to sense
if we're touching avery or not
so this is kind of interesting but the
thing we want to drag into there is
actually
if touching mouse pointer
and the reason we're going to drag this
in is you see this white arrow on here
so this white arrow means that you can
probably change it
and sure enough you can change it to say
um if
touching avery walking so every walking
is the name of that other sprite
so um if touching avery walking
then we want to hide
hide is a command which is over and
looks
so we're going to bring in a hide and
drop it right there
so you can see that the apple has code
that it runs and
avery has code that she runs and if i
hit the green flag right now
avery's going to walk around and as soon
as she touches the apple
it disappears it's gone
and then if you stop your program and
restart it the apple comes back
cool i'd say it's going pretty well
another important thing with games is
that they're fun
right so right now the apple just just
disappears
i think it'd be more fun if our apple
made a little bit of noise
so our apple is going to make a noise
whenever we get it we're going to make a
chomp sound
all sprites have sounds that they
currently know about
let's click on the apple and let's see
what sounds it knows about
sure enough he has a sound called chomp
uh go ahead and play it
oh it kind of sounds like on the apple
so he already has the sound we want if
we wanted more sounds we could add him
but we don't need to for him he's got
the sound we want so let's go back to
our code
so in the code look for sound
[Music]
and what we want to do is we want to
play sound chomp
now there's a couple versions of this
there's play sound until done and then
there's start
sound chomp in this case it doesn't
matter you can put in either one that
you'd want
um so let's go ahead and run it again
and now when we hit the apple
it should make a home chomp sound which
is kind of fun
i don't know if you can hear the chomp
on the video as well but mine worked
really nicely
all right the next thing we're going to
do is we're going to add a variable
so if you remember the main game what it
did is it had many
many different things you had to eat
right and we had to know
was it time to eat the apple or not
because we tried to eat the bananas
first
it would say keep trying food should be
alphabetically
but if you eat the apple first then it
should work right
and so what we need to do is we need to
keep track of the state of the game
the state of the game is a variable so
do this click on variables for me
and click on make a variable
i'm going to name this variable food
you can see that there's a couple
options here it says for all sprites or
for this sprite only
this variable is for everybody in the
whole world so the default of for all
sprites was correct
so i just need to type the word food and
then hit ok
[Music]
now with variables um you can see that
it shows it up here it says food zero
there's a couple things that we always
do with variables we always want to
set their initial value we want to
update them
at an appropriate time and then we want
to use them so
i want to set food to be one so i want
to set it to one when this program
starts up
i'm going to choose to put that code on
avery so click on avery
and so now we're back over in avery's
code
and let's add some code to her what i
want to do is i want to add
set food to and so i'm going to drag
this
and i'm going to put it before the
forever loop
now just for fun that's where it goes
you should put it right there i'm gonna
i'm gonna pretend like i made a mistake
and show you how to fix a mistake
so one thing that happens all the time
when you're coding
is you drop things in the wrong spot and
so let's say i drop this right here
oh no that's that's the wrong spot um so
the question is how do i fix it
the way you do it is you you drag it
over it brings everybody below it with
it
and then you drag the things that you
wanted back right so it's kind of a
two-step process
you'll get used to it with scratch so
where i want it is right here
and i want to set its initial value to
1.
hey also while i'm over here let's go
ahead and make sure that avery starts in
the same spot each time in the game
so put avery to wherever you want her to
start at i'm going to have her start in
the bottom of her room here
and i want her to start there so that's
a motion command so click on motion
so i want the command go to x y
and i want to drop it in here at the
same time i set the variable
i'm going to set her initial position
your numbers don't have to be the same
as mine
and the nice thing about scratch is if
you've got her where you want her
um those it's called the arguments will
get set correctly right so wherever
you put her in the right spot first then
you drag this command over
and things will work quite nicely so
starter somewhere weird
hit the green flag and you'll notice
that she'll go to your starting spot
each time so no matter where she's at
she'll go back to your starting spot all
right so this variable we made it we set
its initial value
um now let's see if we can change it at
an appropriate time
click on your apple so your apple
if he's touching avery he needs to hide
he needs to make a chomp sound
by the way the order of those two
commands doesn't matter at all you can
have it swapped and that's fine
the other thing we want to do is we want
to
[Music]
increment the variable so let's just go
ahead and
quickly go to variables
and find change food by one
and drop it in here
[Music]
so let's go ahead and run it again and
this won't be that exciting but if you
notice food is currently one
but after i eat the apple food changes
to two
right so things are going pretty good
now the next thing we're going to do is
a little tricky so i want to only be
able to eat the apple
if food is currently one so here's what
i'm going to do
i'm going to take the code that i've got
in here
and i'm going to set it over to the side
so i still want that code but i'm just
going to set it over to the side
now what i want to do is i want to have
an if else statement
so we've we've learned about if
statements they were over in control
and this time what we want is we want
the more complex version it kind of
looks like a big letter e
and put in uh an if else statement
and so when we're touching avery we want
to check
is food equal to the correct number and
in this case
one so if food is equal to one we want
to let you eat it
if food is not one then we want to show
like an error message
so here's what we're gonna do we're
gonna go to operators
and we're going to find the one that
says equals it's about six or seven down
here
[Music]
and so if our variable food is equal to
the apples the first thing so if our
variable food is equal to one
then we're going to do stuff go into
variables
and drag food into that other white
circle
i did that kind of fast so if you need
to pause the video that's fine
but i went into operators and i grabbed
this equals
i changed the right hand side to be one
then i went into variables and i grabbed
food and i put that on the left hand
side
so if food is one then i want to do this
stuff that we were doing over here so
i'm going to drop this into the top
now what should we do if food is not one
does anybody want to say what we should
do if food is not one bowen do you have
any ideas
do you remember what uh what this
program did so if i tried to eat the
banana
what did it say yeah so if it's not the
right time we want to say a message
so let's go into looks
[Music]
um and grab this say hello for two
seconds
and then you should probably have an
adult type your message because it takes
forever to type
so what i'm going to say is i'm going to
say keep trying
oops sorry i'm going to say keep trying
and then i'll say
food should be eaten
alphabetically
now have an adult type that for you
because it takes a while to type
all right so let's go ahead and try it
now this time
we only have one food it's the apple
it's the correct time to eat the apple
so if you
if you hit the apple it should go chomp
and it should be successful we've never
seen this message still
let's make another sprite let's add some
bananas
so to add another sprite this is kind of
a review click on this green circle down
here
um and find the bananas uh for me it's
still pretty high in the order
by the way eventually we're going to go
to the food category and this will have
all the different foods we're going to
eat so i'm going to go with banana
if you want to do bread bread also
starts with b that'd be fine
if you want to eat a bowl i suppose you
could but i wouldn't recommend eating
bowls
i'm going to decide where the bananas
need to go into my figure i'm going to
make them a little sneaky
i'm going to say that these bananas are
sitting over here at the edge of the bed
now what we want to do is the bananas
need to have all the same code that the
apple had
the only thing that's different is
whether this food is equal to one or
food is equal to two
but it's mostly the exact same i do not
want to type it all
and sprite has a real or scratch has a
really good trick for this
go to the apple and drag the code from
the apple
and drop it right here on the banana it
takes a little bit of getting used to
and you can see that whenever i did it
the banana kind of wiggled a little
and so if i drop it right there now it
it it's a copy paste is what happened
so now if i go to my apple i can see
that my apple has this code
and if i go to my banana the banana has
this code i can tell that neel is
struggling with this drag and drop
mommy may have to help her some so both
of them have the same code
there's one thing that needs to be
different and it's this
if food is equal to one the banana is
the second food
right so change it to a two
let's try it again so now
if i try to eat the banana first um
it'll say keep drying
food should be alphabetically
i try to eat the apple first it'll eat
it
now i'm going to go eat the banana wow
so you can see it worked if we did the
banana
now we're going to mass produce some
food and my goal is for you
to do this on your own i'm going to help
you kind of sort it with one more
and then i want you to just kind of make
a whole bunch so
to add the c i'm just going to do it
quickly here
i'm going to say choose a sprite i'm
going to click on food
and i'm going to pick a seafood i'm
going to pick cake
so now the cake is in here
and now i'm going to arrange the cake to
be a certain size
the cake then needs the same code
so i'm going to drag the code onto the
cake
and the cake is the third food so i
switch it to a three
so i want you to mass produce that for a
couple different fruits maybe go out to
like
egg or if you want to you can go to
fortune cookie there's there's one
problem still with the sound
but we'll we'll fix that so i'm going to
pause the video
i'm going to let you add all the foods
that you want to add
and then we're going to fix the sounds
together after you add them so pause the
video and go add your foods
all right so our family had to take a
little break maybe you guys it's a good
time to take a break as well but
um i got mine added um so i've got apple
and it says food one check yours with me
so make sure your apple says food one
then click on your banana make sure it
says food too
your cake or whatever c you've got food
three
donut for egg
five fortune cookie six
now if you try it um it will work right
now
but the sounds may not work so when i
eat my apple
uh where did my apple go to my apple's
right underneath my cake
um when i eat my apple it made noise
my banana actually made noise but then
after that they quit making noise um
so why did that oh the donut made noise
um so why do some make noise and others
don't make noise
i'm gonna also move my cake a little bit
because my cake and my apple were
right on top of each other by the way
one trick for bringing them all back is
if you just hit
start and then stop immediately then
they all come back right so i like that
trick
so that you can actually see things so
why didn't they make noise
so the apple you can see it says start
sound chomp
and then if you go to his tab he's got a
chomp sound so he's going to work fine
banana actually has the same code he
plays chomp
but you can see his sounds may not have
a chomp in it so what we want to do is
on the banana i want to switch it to
a sound that he does have so he has bite
on cake
instead of chomp i want to switch it to
a sound he does have i'm going to play
birthday
which is actually a little long but
that's okay donut
instead of chomp i want i'll go with
bite
egg i think you see the pattern so
switch it to a sound he does have egg
has pop
that's fine and fortune cookie what's
fortune cookie guy he's got pop
oh oh well if you wanted to add more
sounds you could play around in the
sound tab
but i quickly lose half an hour when i
let my kids go play the sound tab
um so we're just going to fix it like
that so now they should all make noise
so my campers are going to make a ton of
noise here so i get the apple
um banana
birthday you're gonna hear for like an
hour
[Music]
ah donut egg
fortune cookie cool so i think that
worked pretty well
one advanced thing you can do by the way
on on the birthday cake its song was
kind of long
so you don't have to do this this is
optional i'm going to go into the
birthday cake and the sounds
and i'm going to click faster a few
times
and so it'll play a nice fast happy
birthday but it was taken too long
so i went into the sounds on cake and i
clicked faster
one or two times right all right
we're gonna add one more feature you
guys up for one more feature
one more feature when the game is over
nothing happens
and it would be kind of nice if
something happened
that said like congratulations or a
great job or you win
or something like that so we're going to
add one more piece of code
to avery so click on your avery sprite
her code should look like this
and we're going to add an if statement
in here so the if statements were over
in control
in the control area find if
and just like we did for all the foods
we're going to see if that variable
is a certain number you can see that i
had six foods
so my variable ends at a seven so for
avery
i'm gonna say if food is equal to seven
then i'm gonna play congratulations you
win things like that so i'm going to go
to operators
i'm going to find the equals operator
this is just like we did before i'm
going to do variables
i'm gonna do food is equal to seven
all right so i've got that in there if
you ever need to pause it by the way
just pause the video and put that in
there
so when we win the game we want to do a
couple things first i want to say
congratulations
so saying things is over in looks
and i this time i do care which i grab i
want to make sure to grab
say hello without any time delay on it
so i just want to say say hello
and you can put whatever congratulations
message you want again you might want to
have an adult type for you
so i'm going to say you win alphabet
breakfast
so type whatever message you'd like and
make sure it's the version
that doesn't have the delay on it
alright so i typed that for my camper
now we're ready to add a sound
now avery only has the sound of pop
that's not good enough i want a funner
sound
so make sure you've got avery selected
go to her sound
area and let's add a new sound so come
down here to the lower left corner
and say choose a sound
and the sound i want you to add is dance
celebration
so there's a couple ways to find dance
i chose to type in part of the word
dance because i knew that it was one of
the options
and i can see right here the second one
is dance celebration
so i'm going to click in the middle of
this white box
now that i've added the sound avery can
now play the sound in our code right
so i've added the sound here then i go
into the code
and on sounds this time i want play
sound
until done so i'm going to play this
and it defaulted to dance celebration
for me which was nice until done
and then the very last thing i'm going
to do is i'm going to end the program
so after i drag on play sound until done
i'm the last going to grab a stop all
so it's in control it's near the bottom
and it's a stop haul now make sure that
this gets dropped into the correct spot
so it needs to go i'm inside this inner
loop
and that's our last line of code so it's
time to try it
and then i'm going to walk around i'm
going to see how my campers did
so what should happen now is i should be
able to play my game
banana cake
[Music]
donut egg and then whenever i get the
fortune cookie
i should do my dance celebration
all right so i think that mine is ready
to go uh but i'm more interested to see
uh how my campers did today uh neela do
you want to show us yours
yeah all right let's see it neela so
neela has a unicorn as we know
um and neela is walking around with the
unicorn
and she's got her sounds
and so she's got
cheesy puss for c donut
egg and fortune cookie
great job all right bowen let's see
yours let's see how bowen did bowen's is
a penguin theme
so bowens has littler food so he's gonna
walk around and he's gonna eat his apple
great job and then his oh looks like
you've got bread down there bowen
and then a cake and then a doughnut
all right and then um your egg which is
way up in the sun
and then your fortune cookie
oh you made that one faster great job
bowen high five bud
all right keegan you're next in birth
order let's see uh
let's see yours so keegan is nine and
he's a big old stinker pot
so his are teeny tiny so you gotta
really zoom in to see his apple
uh it's in the poster so he's got an
apple
and then i have no idea where his bee is
oh it's a basketball
[Music]
so he can see him with his infinitely
small vision
but i can't even see him
all right how many do you got left bud i
don't even know one more
oh and he's got a lot of foods he added
and then he's got a song there great job
bud
all right assistant you're up next
sissy's our family artist
so of course she's got a craziness going
on she's got a butterfly
um and she's got flowers and she's got
food eaten
she hides it after the song's over
great job this and then we're going to
get to her celebration
she's also got a fancy dance party all
right did you guys have fun building
your uh
building your program today yes all
right
i want to say one last thing before we
let you go so campers you can just kind
of
bear with me and listen if you want to
publish your project you can click on
the word share here
and it'll make a public page that other
people can look at
you do have to be signed in to do that
and then this url right here you could
send to a friend or family
and then they could see your project as
well so i think that's all i've got
um really i just wanted to make sure
that you know a couple things
you can sit on my lap first off is
coding is fun
uh you can totally do it neela is five
this is her first coding experience ever
um and she's learning little bits at a
time right
but we hopefully know that different
sprites have different code
the code runs in order and there's lots
of great things we learned today
but we've got a whole week of this and
each day will hopefully get easier and
easier for you
so we loved having you join us we hope
to see you again tomorrow
bye
[Music]